While loops are really good at repeating things for as long as some condition stays true,
遇到只要条件一直为真就要重复执行代码的情况 while 循环真的很实用
like while money spent is less than
比如当花钱少于一定金额的时候
a certain amount or while waiting for the time to reach a certain point.
或时间未到就继续等待的时候
But sometimes, we want to repeat things for a certain specific number of times.
可是有时候 我们想在一定次数内重复某件事
Imagine there was a warning that we wanted to display the message for exactly 10 times.
想象有这么个警告 我们就想发出整整十次警告提示
Let's have a look at an example.
来看看这个例子
Let's declare a function called raiseAlarm that would print out a certain number of
声明一个叫 raiseAlarm (报警) 的函数 该函数会输出一定条数的警告信息
warning messages based on the value of an input argument and return nothing.
这个条数是由输入参数的值决定的 但该函数不会返回任何事物
Hence, public void raiseAlarm and it will accept the argument number
于是 输入 public void raiseAlarm 该函数以 numOfWarnings (警告次数) 为参数
of warnings which is an integer because we were
该参数为一个整数
going to specify a specific number that we want to display.
因为我们会说明要输出警告的具体次数
To stop after a specific number of repetitions,
要在重复了一定次数后停止执行代码
we need to keep track of every iteration the loop has successfully completed.
我们需要对循坏每次成功的迭代进行跟踪
To do that, we need to declare an integer variable just before the loop starts.
要实现该操作 我们需要在循环前声明一个整数变量
Let's call it i for iteration,
就管它叫 i 吧 即iteration (迭代) 的首字母
and we'll initialize it to one.
然后将其初始值设为 1
This is usually referred to as the loop counter.
通常我们管这个叫循环计数器
Then, we want to make sure our loop would only keep
然后 我们得确保只要 i 仍小于或等于 numOfWarnings
going as long as it's still less than or equal to the number of warnings.
循环就会不断执行
So, this would be our loop condition right here.
因此我们的循环条件会是这样
This is basically saying that we want to repeat this instruction here,
这里的意思是 我们想重复这条指令
print line warning for as long as i
“println (Warning) ” (输出警告)
is still less than or equal to the number of warnings.
除非 i 不再小于或等于 numOfWarnings
The last thing we need to do is to keep
最后我们要做的
track of the number of iterations that we've done.
是跟踪迭代次数
This is done by updating our loop counter i by adding one to it inside our loop.
因此 我们要更新循环计数器 i 在循环里给它加 1
So each iteration, our i increases by one.
每次迭代 i 都会加 1
This statement here is called the loop increment.
这个语句称为循环增量
As a shorthand however,
不过要简写的话
this increment here can be written as i++ which means exactly the same thing.
这个增量可以写成 i++ 意思完全一样
Simply, increase i by one or add one to i.
很简单 就是 i 增加 1 或者给 i 加 1 的意思
You could use either the shorthand version or the longhand version,
你可以使用简写 也可以全部写出来
it doesn't matter, they would do the exact same thing.
无所谓 它们的功能完全相同
However, as we going to see later on,
不过 我们等下就会看到
this shorthand makes our program a lot more readable. So, there we go.
用简写的话 程序可读性会强很多 好了
With these three important parts of our while loop,
有了这三个重要部分
we managed to build a loop that would repeat something for a specific number of times.
我们的 while 循环就可以以特定次数重复做某事了
Let's trace it and see what's happening.
我们来跟踪这个循环 看看怎么样
Okay, let's assume we're going to call this function with a parameter value of five,
假设我们要在参数值为 5 的情况下调用这个函数
making our number of warnings variable equal to five.
于是令变量 numOfWarnings 等于 5
First, we start by initializing our variable i to one,
首先 我们把变量 i 初始化为 1
and then we reach our loop where it starts comparing i to the number of warnings.
然后就到了循环这里 开始比较 i 和 numOfWarnings 的值
Because number of warnings was passed in as five,
因为 numOfWarnings 被设为 5
so it's comparing whether i is less than or equal to five, which is true.
所以要比较的是 i 是否小于或等于 5 比较结果为真
Since it's true, we step inside our loop and we start executing the commands inside it.
既然为真 我们就进入循环 开始执行里面的指令
The first one is basically saying print line warning.
第一个语句说的是 输出一行警告信息
So, our output would have a warning in it.
所以我们的输出里会有一个警告
The second statement is incrementing i,
第二个语句是给 i 增量
simply adding one to i and updating it,
也就是只给 i 加 1 并更新 i
making our i value two.
使 i 值变为 2
Then reach our end of our loop,
然后就到了循环尾部
so we go back up and we repeat that condition,
于是我们回到这上面来 重复条件
would check if two is less than or equal to the number
判断 2 是否小于或等于 numOfWarnings
of warnings which in that case is five.
而这里 numOfWarnings 等于 5
So it's still true,
所以结果仍为真
meaning that we step inside the loop again and we print out the warning one more time.
也就是我们又得进入循环 再输出一次警告
Again, we increment i making it one more and then we reach our end of our loop,
再来 给 i 增加 1 然后到达循环尾部
go back up to our comparison,
回到比较来
and three is still less than or equal to five,
3 还是小于或等于 5
so we step back in and we print out the warning message.
所以再进来 输出警告信息
Increment i again and go back and check
再给 i 增量 再回来判断循环条件
our loop condition which is still less than or equal to five,
还是小于或等于 5
so I stepped back into our loop,
于是我再进到循环
print one more time,
再输出一次
increment i making it five,
给 i 增量 使其为 5
and then we step back to the top of that loop comparing five to the number of warnings,
现在我们回到循环开端 比较 5 和 numOfWarnings 的值
which is still less than or equal to five because five is equal to five.
仍然是小于或等于 5 因为 5 等于 5
So that's true. We step into our loop and then we print out warning again.
所以条件为真 进入循环 再次输出警告
And then we increment i making it equal to six,
给 i 增量 使其为 6
go back up, do our check.
回来 做判断
Is six less than or equal to five?
6 小于或等于 5 吗？
No. This means we've reached this part.
不 这就意味着在进行这部分比较的时候
This condition is false.
条件为假
So we do not step into our loop and we just exit.
所以我们不会进入循环 直接跳出来了
And that's the end of our function.
函数由此结束
So, if we call this function with a parameter five,
所以 如果我们调用这个函数 设其参数为 5 的话
we see warning printed out five times.
我们就能看到程序输出五次警告